<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Christian sword and buckler, or, A letter by D. Sprint to a man seuen yeares grieuously afflicted in conscience and fearefully possessed by the Diuel very comfortable and commodious to withstand the assaults of Sathan.</title>
            <author>Sprint, John, d. 1623.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 24 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12799</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23108.2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4917</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24073746</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24073746</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27149</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12799)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27149)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1842:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Christian sword and buckler, or, A letter by D. Sprint to a man seuen yeares grieuously afflicted in conscience and fearefully possessed by the Diuel very comfortable and commodious to withstand the assaults of Sathan.</title>
                  <author>Sprint, John, d. 1623.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B. Alsop for Samuel Rand and are to be sold at his shop at Holborne Bridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁸(-A1) B⁴ (last leaf blank).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Consolation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27149:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27149:1"/>
            <p> THE CHRISTIAN SWORD AND BVCKLER.</p>
            <p>OR, A Letter ſent by D. SPRINT, to a man ſeuen yeares grieuouſly afflicted in conſcience, and fearefully poſſeſſed by the Diuel.</p>
            <p>Very comfortable and commodious to withſt and the aſſaults of Sathan.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>B. Alſop</hi> for <hi>Samuel Rand</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at Holborne Bridge.</p>
            <p>1623.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:27149:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:27149:2"/>
            <head>THE CHRISTIAN SWORD AND BVCKLER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR I am not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindfull of your Letter, though by occaſion of buſines I haue beene let. I commend your care to ſeeke comfort from the ordinance of God, that is his <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 14.</note> Miniſters, who are commaunded of God to comfort the feeble minded, <note place="margin">Eſa. 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</note> and to ſpeake comfortably to <hi>Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> and to cry vnto her, that her warfare is accompliſhed that her iniquitie is pardoned; As Chriſt was annoynted, ſo are his Miniſters ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to preach the Goſpell to the <note place="margin">Luke 4. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> poore, deliuerance to the captiue, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couery
<pb facs="tcp:27149:3"/> of fight to the blinde and to ſet at libertie ſuch as are bruſed.</p>
            <p>Wherefore ſeeing you haue entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me helpe, I will (by Gods aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance) ſatisfie your deſire.</p>
            <p>Your caſe was ſtrange to be holden as a creature ſenceleſſe for ſeuen whole yeares. But others alſo haue beene holden with the like; <hi>Nabuchadnezar</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Dan. 4. 29.</note> King of Babell was turned out a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing among beaſts. 7. yeares; yea Gods children haue beene far worſe afflicted, as that Daughter of <hi>Abraham</hi> was for 18. yeares bound of Sathan. The man <note place="margin">Luke 13. 16 40. 5.</note> whom our Sauiour cured had beene diſeaſed 38. yeares which are far a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the diſtance of your ſicknes, wherefore you ought not to thinke the worſe of your ſelfe, for nothing hath befallen vnto you but that which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaineth <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10. 13.</note> vnto man; Nay you ought to comfort your heart in your afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for as you know the ſender which is God, and the cauſe which is your ſinne: So now you know your deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerer, and the cauſe which is his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; for it is the Lord who killeth and <note place="margin">1. Sam. 2. 6.</note> maketh aliue, bringeth downe to the
<pb facs="tcp:27149:3"/> graue and raiſeth vp: And by how much greater your croſſe hath beene, by ſo much the greater was your deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance; The mighty power of God vpon your body, and his rich mercy on your ſoule, hath the more appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that ſo the more he might be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and your heart comforted; for you may argue thus; The Lord might haue in iuſtice deſtroyed me, yet hee hath in mercy ſpared me; the Lord might haue choſen whether hee would haue deliuered me or not; But in great mercy he rather choſe to deliuer mee; The Lord might haue left mee my health, and withdrawne his grace from me, and giuen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ouer to the power of Sathan: But hee hath reſtored my health and vnderſtanding, and renued my Grace;</p>
            <p>Hereby I ſee God dearely loueth me, which I could neuer ſee if I had not thus beene afflicted; How ſhould I hence forth diſtruſt his prouidence, doubt of his promiſes, diſpayre of his mercy, why would I not reſt aſſured, and ſecured of his preſent and perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all loue to imbrace me, his mercy to
<pb facs="tcp:27149:4"/> pardon me, his prouidence to defend me, his goodnes to compaſſe me and to worke all euils for my good; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my ſoule returne vnto thy reſt, for <note place="margin">Pſal. 116. 7. 8. 9. 12. 13.</note> the Lord hath been beneficiall to thee; he hath deliuered my ſoule from death, and mine eyes from teares, &amp; my feete <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> falling, I ſhall walke before the Lord in the land of the liuing, what ſhall I render to the Lord for all his benefits, I will take the cup of Salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and call vpon the name of the Lord.</p>
            <p>The Lord was ready to ſaue mee, <note place="margin">Pſa. 38. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</note> therefore I will ſing my ſong all the dayes of my life in the houſe of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Thus may you comfort your ſelfe, yet meaſure not Gods loue ſo much by your deliuerance, as by his grace which nature gaue you not, nor hath God ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away.</p>
            <p>For as afflictions are no certaine to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of Gods anger: ſo deliuerance, is not alwayes a token of his fauour.</p>
            <p>For he gaue the Iſralites their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, but he ſent heauines into their ſoules: God may in mercy lengthen <note place="margin">Pſal. 106. 15</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:27149:4"/> our afflictions, &amp; in iudgement make an end of it. The table of the wicked <note place="margin">Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> is a ſnare vnto them, and their proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie their ruine, but it is good for Gods <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> children that they haue beene afflicted that they may learne his ſtatutes; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines is Gods beſt portion which is <note place="margin">1. Tim. 6. 6, &amp; 4. 8.</note> great gaine, and is profitable for all things, hauing the promiſes of the life preſent, and of that which is to come; Wherefore proue the grace that is in you and to meaſure the loue of God vnto you; Try what godly griefe you haue for ſinne; what vexation at your wants, what feare of God, what faith in Ieſus Chriſt, what loue of Gods children, what delight in the word and Miniſtery, what deſire of the grace you lacke, what feruency in prayer, what chearefulnes in prayſing God, what care of well doing, and readynes to doe the will of God, what patience in ſuffering croſſes from God, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe from man, what holy Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, what gracious ſpeeches, what diligence in your calling, what dutiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to your ſuperiors, what purpoſe of heart to cleaue vnto the Lord; theſe are
<pb facs="tcp:27149:5"/> the ſparkles of Gods Image, the fruites of his ſpirit, the effects of his grace, the aſſurance of his election, the certaine tokens of his preſence; For <note place="margin">2. Cor. 1. 5. 2</note> the Lord is with vs, whiles wee are with him; and he draweth neare vnto <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m. 4. 8.</note> vs when we draw neare vnto him.</p>
            <p>Now touching the temptations of Sathan that doe trouble you, perceiue when God hath done with you, the Diuell taketh you in hand, God af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicteth your body, and the Diuel your ſoule. But as God brought you from ſicknes to health: So thinke that God can bring you from temptations to victorie; that being prepared by af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction in Soule and body, you may both ſerue him in this life, and liue with him in the next.</p>
            <p>Euery temptation of a Chriſtian, is a ground of ſtrong conſolation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Sathans onſets argue that wee are none of his; for the Dragon ſtrikes not at his owne ſouldiers (for King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes <note place="margin">Reu. 12. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> deuided are at an end) but at <hi>Mychaell</hi> and his Angels; If Chriſt <note place="margin">Math. 12. 25</note> had not beene the Sonne of God, hee would not ſo fiercely haue affailed him;
<pb facs="tcp:27149:5"/> Warryors neuer beſiege nor batter Cities they haue woone, ſo Satan ſeekes not the ſoules he hath deuored; he rageth moſt at thoſe he cannot get, <note place="margin">Reuel 12. 13 14. 15. 17.</note> and is moſt buſie with thoſe he hath leaſt to doe; when this ſtrong man keepeth his Pallace in mens ſoules, the <note place="margin">Luke 11. 21.</note> things that he poſſeſſeth are in peace; and when he is reſtrained and muzze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the power of God, hee rageth at the perſons, and roareth in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of Gods deere Children; your temptations come not to you by chance, but by the will of God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out whoſe leaue he cannot touch ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">Iob. 1. 10.</note> man or beaſt; But God hath an hand to limit Sathan, and direct his <note place="margin">Math. 8. 31.</note> temptation for our good, as he hath an hand to let him looſe for our tryall and vexation; Hereby hee humbleth the <note place="margin">2. Cor. 12. 17.</note> pride, tryeth the patience, ſifteth the faith and worketh the victory of his <note place="margin">Iob. 1. 11. 12. Luke 22. 31 Reuel. 12. 11 Math. 4. 1.</note> beloued Saints: It is Gods ſpirit that leadeth Gods Children to be tempted of the Diuel and he that leades them into the battle can giue them victory; <note place="margin">1. Io. 4. 4.</note> For greater is hee that is in vs then, he that is in the world; The Serpents <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 15.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:27149:6"/> head is cruſhed by the ſeede of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; The Diuel is conquered and caſt <note place="margin">Reu. 12. 10. 12.</note> out of heauen, and is come downe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the inhabitants of the earth, ſo that Angels cannot ſeparate vs from the <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 38. 39. Luke 22. 31. 32.</note> loue of God in Chriſt, when Sathan hindereth vs, Chriſt prayeth that our faith faile not, for he euer liueth to make requeſt for vs; when the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger of Satan is ſent to buffet vs, Gods grace is ſufficient for vs; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">2. Cor. 12. 9</note> you muſt reioyce in theſe tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, becauſe it is for the tryall of your faith and patience; And for Sathan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">Iam. 1. 2. 3.</note> figge for him, reſiſt him onely and hee will flie from you, pray to your Father to free you from temptations, and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he doe not free you from them, yet he <note place="margin">Iam. 4. 7.</note> will deliuer you from euill.</p>
            <p>The particuler poynts of his temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, I will briefely touch: Hee tel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you, that the word of God is falſe: This is the firſt leſſon that the Diuel teacheth, and it is his way to mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> men Atheiſt; But you muſt tell hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that God is as true of his word; as h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is falſe of his; God is the God of truth; <note place="margin">Pſal. 31. 5. Io. 8. 44.</note> and the Diuel is the father of a lye. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is not poſſible that God ſhould lye. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:27149:6"/> is not poſſible but the Diuel ſhould lye; <note place="margin">Heb. 6. 18.</note> ſay you vnto your ſoule I muſt beleeue the truth, and not a lye, leaſt I turne <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 25.</note> Gods truth into a lye; for he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth not God hath made him a lyer; <note place="margin">1. Io. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</note> I will rather beleeue the creator then the creature; the maker then the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer of man: and that which will ſaue me then that which will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne me; yea let God be true, &amp; euery <note place="margin">Rom. 3. 4. Iam. 1. 18.</note> Diuel and man a lyer; As for the word of god it is the word of truth it is righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes altogether, euery word there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is pure &amp; endureth for euer; This the <note place="margin">Pſal. 19. 9.</note> godly ſhow, who onely loue it, this the wicked ſhew who only hate it; this the <note place="margin">Pro. 39. 5. 1, Pet. 1. 25.</note> ſpirit witneſſeth in the hearts of Gods Children, this the power thereof pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimeth in the conuerſion of ſoules: this experience of all times and places maketh euident, the wicked know it to their coſt, (both men and Diuels) the faithfull to their comfort.</p>
            <p>Next if Satan ſeeke to lay your ſinnes before your eyes; thereto you muſt lay the ſufferings of Chriſt before your eyes; If he accuſe you, tell him the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſer <note place="margin">Reu. 12. 10.</note> of brethren is caſt out; If hee
<pb facs="tcp:27149:7"/> charge your conſcience with your ſins; aske him who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods choſen? If he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om. 8. 33. 34.</note> you for them; ſay it is God that iuſtifieth, who ſhall then condemne. If he ſay your ſinnes are many, and more then can be pardoned; tell him where <note place="margin">Rom. 15. 20.</note> ſinne aboundeth grace ouer abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: If he ſay you are the greateſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in the world; tell him it is true, but Chriſt came into the world to ſaue ſinners, whereof I am the chiefe: If he <note place="margin">1. Tim. 1. 15.</note> alleadge the greatnes of the guilt, ſay, though my ſinnes be as red as Scarlet, <note place="margin">Eſa 1 18.</note> yet hee will make them as white as Snowe: If he ſay ſuppoſe ſome of thy ſinnes be clenſed, yet not all, ſay that the bloud of Chriſt clenſeth vs from all <note place="margin">1. Io. 1. 7.</note> ſinnes: If he ſay Chriſt dyed for ſome but not for all; ſay he is the reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <note place="margin">1. Io. 2. 2.</note> of the ſinnes of the whole world; he is the Sauiour of all men but ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of them that beleeue: If he ſay ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe God pardon thee, it is but for a ſeaſon till thou ſinne againe, tell him <note place="margin">1. Tim. 4 10. Ier. 32. 31. 34</note> againe of the new couenant of God, which ſayeth, I will forgiue their ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie and will remember their ſinnes
<pb facs="tcp:27149:7"/> no more; If he ſay in all this thou pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumeſt, <note place="margin">2. Cor. 7. 10</note> ſhew him your godly ſorrow, which cauſeth repentance to ſaluation; If he ſay how knoweſt thou whether God will accept of thy repentance or not, tell him if we acknowledge our <note place="margin">1. Io. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſinnes, God is faithfull and iuſt to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue our Sinnes, and to clenſe vs from all vnrighteouſnes; If hee ſay thy ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row is diſpaire, examine your ſelfe <note place="margin">2. Cor. 13. 5</note> whether you be in the faith, and ſay to God, I beleeue Lord helpe my vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leife; <note place="margin">Marke 9. 24</note> If he ſay thy faith is fained dead and falſe; ſay vnto him, hee that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth <note place="margin">1. Io. 5. 10.</note> in the Sonne hath witnes in himſelfe, as for thee O Sathan, I will <note place="margin">Iam. 2. 18.</note> ſhew thee my faith by my wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kes. If he ſay thy obedience is but fained dead and falſe, and you are but an Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite; ſay of yourſelfe, I know nothing by my ſelfe yet am I not thereby iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; <note place="margin">1. Cor. 4 4.</note> Turne vnto God and ſay, O that my wayes were directed to keepe thy <note place="margin">Pſal. 1. 9. 5. 80.</note> ſtatutes; Keepe my heart vpright i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thy ſtatutes that I be not aſhamed: if he ſay thou a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t accurſed, becauſe thou contine weſt not in all things that are written; ſay againe, Chriſt hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed <note place="margin">Gal. 3. 13.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:27149:8"/> me from the curſe of the law, when he was made a curſe for one; If he ſay thy coruptions be ſtrange and <note place="margin">Rom. 7. 24. 25.</note> many; cry out O miſerable man that I am, who ſhall deliuer me from this body of death; I thanke God through Ieſus Chriſt: Pray vnto God create a <note place="margin">Pſal. 51. 10.</note> cleane heart O Lord, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enue a right ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit within me; If he ſay for all this thou ſhalt be condemned, becauſe Gods iudgements be exact, and giueth euery man according to his workes; ſay there <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 1.</note> is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt, to them that walke not after the fleſh but after the ſpirit: laſtly if he ſay, yet thou canſt haue no peace of conſcience but perpetuall wound; ſay, the Lord ſpeaketh peace to his people <note place="margin">Pſal. 85. 8.</note> and to his Saints, that they turne not againe to their folly, For being iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <note place="margin">Rom, 5. 1.</note> by faith we haue peace towards God through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>I know that Diuel may proceed and ſay, thou art not choſen; But you muſt ſay vnto him: that God choſe vs in <note place="margin">Eph. 1. 4.</note> Chriſt that we ſhould be holy: and I am ſure that God hath choſen to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe <note place="margin">Pſal. 4. 3.</note> the man that is godly; vertue
<pb facs="tcp:27149:8"/> ioyned to our faith makes our calling and election ſure, for ſuch as God hath predeſtinated them hath he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, wherefore ſo long as Gods grace <note place="margin">Luke 10. 20.</note> remaineth in me, ſo long I will reioyce that my name is witten in the booke of life: But Sathan may obiect, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe thou be now in the fauour of thy God, yet thou maiſt fall away from <note place="margin">Rom. 11. 29.</note> grace; he may withdraw his ſpirit. To this you may anſwere this againe, the guifts and callings of God are <note place="margin">Ier 13. 3.</note> without repentance; i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he loue vs hee loued vs from euerlaſting, and loueth <note place="margin">Io. 13. 1.</note> vs to the end. No creature ſhalbe able <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 38. 39. Pſal. 23. 6.</note> to ſeperate vs from the loue of God in Chriſt; kindnes and mercy ſhall fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me all the dayes of my. life, and this God is our God for euer and euer <note place="margin">Pſal. 48. 14.</note> he ſhalbe our guide vnto the death. But he may ſay, that Gods minde may alter, and he may hate them for ſinne, whom he loued of mercy: God an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth <note place="margin">Mat. 3. 6.</note> for himſelfe, I am the Lord I chaunge not, and ye Sounes of <hi>Iacob</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 15. 29</note> are not conſumed, for God is not as man that hee ſhould repent. Ieſus <note place="margin">Heb. 13. 8.</note> Chriſt that was yeſterday, is the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:27149:9"/> to day, the ſame alſo is for euer; Gods couenaunt of life and peace is euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting. <note place="margin">Ier. 33. 20. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.</note> If Sathan thou canſt breake Gods couenaunt of the day and night, that there ſhall not be day and night, in their ſeaſon, then may Gods coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant be broken with his children, for God hath ſaid vnto his choſen. The mountaines ſhall remoue, and the hills <note place="margin">Eſa. 54. 10.</note> fall downe, but my mercy ſhall not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from thee, neither ſhall this coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of my peace fall away, faith the Lord which hath compaſſion on thee. For that mercy and free grace which <note place="margin">Rom, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 10.</note> moued God to accept vs when wee were ſinners, ſtrangers, enemies and children of wrath, and to reconcile vs by the death of his Sonne, muſt much more moue him, (being reconciled) to accept vs, and to ſaue vs by the life of Chriſt. Thus the foundation of God remaineth ſure.</p>
            <p>Yet Sathan may reply, ſuppoſe there be no alteration or chaunge in God: yet in thee there is: He is ſtrong, but thou art weake. But <hi>Peter</hi> anſwereth <note place="margin">2. Pet. 1. 5.</note> that we are not kept by our owne ſtrength, but by the power of God vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:27149:9"/> Saluation, and I ſhall ouercome by <note place="margin">Reu. 12. 11.</note> the bloud of the lamb, for in his owne <note place="margin">1. Sam. 2. 9.</note> might ſhall no man be ſtrong: ſuppoſe then I may fall, and that moſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly, as <hi>Dauid, Salomon,</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> did: yet though I fall I ſhall no be caſt <note place="margin">Pſal. 37. 24. 23.</note> off: for the Lord putteth his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vnder me: The pathes of man are directed by the Lord, he will keepe the feete of his Saints. Wherefore reioyce not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <note place="margin">Sam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 9.</note> me O mine enemies, though I fall I ſhall riſe, when I ſit in darknes <note place="margin">Mica. 7. 8. 7</note> the Lord ſhalbe a light vnto me.</p>
            <p>If Sathan vrge you further thus, how dareſt thou preſume of Gods aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, thou haſt not Gods grace at thy commaund, ſhew him the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of God, confirmed and ſealed by the bloud of Ieſus Chriſt, who ſaith, <note place="margin">Ier. 31. 33.</note> I will write my law in their hearts, I will make an euerlaſting couenant <note place="margin">Ier. 32. 40.</note> with them, that I will neuer turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from them, to doe them good, I will put my feare into their hearts, that they ſhall not depart from me, I will giue them a new heart and a new <note place="margin">Eze 36. 26. 27. &amp; 11. 19, 20.</note> ſpirit, I will take the ſtony heart out of their bodies, and I will giue them a
<pb facs="tcp:27149:10"/> heart of fleſh, I will put my ſpirit within them, and cauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>em to walke in my ſtatutes. It is moſt true we are not ſufficient of our ſelues, to thinke <note place="margin">2. Cor. 3. 5.</note> any thing of our ſelues, but our ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciencie is of God: As no man cometh vnto Chriſt, except the father drawe <note place="margin">Io. 6. 44. 65. Io. 15. 5.</note> him, ſo without Chriſt we can doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: Yet through the helpe of Chriſt which ſtrengtheneth me, I ſhalbe able <note place="margin">Phil. 4. 13. Phil. 1. 6.</note> to doe all things. And hee that hath begun this good worke within mee, will performe it vntill the day of Ieſus Chriſt: And his good ſpirit ſhall leade <note place="margin">Pſa. 143. 10 Eph. 4. 30.</note> me into the land of righteouſnes, and ſeale me to the day of my redemption.</p>
            <p>As for the helpe that Sathan offereth thee. Aske him, how hee can helpe another that cannot helpe himſelfe, and how ſhould one truſt the faith of a deceauour: Hee offered the world vnto our Sauiour Chriſt, and tolde him that the world was his, but he tolde a <note place="margin">Luke 4. 6.</note> lye; for albeit he be called the god of this world, becauſe he ruleth in the <note place="margin">1. Cor. 4. 4.</note> children of diſobedience; yet the earth is the Lords, and all that therein is, the <note place="margin">Eph. 2. 2. Pſa. 24. 1.</note> world and all that dwell therein.
<pb facs="tcp:27149:10"/> Wherefore although the wicked of the world fall downe and worſhip him, to gaine farre ſmaller matters then the world, by lying, ſwearing, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwearing, deceiuing, and oppreſſing, and ſuch euil courſes, yet you muſt vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly refuſe this offer, with auoide Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, and come behinde me Sathan, for it is written thou ſhalt worſhip the <note place="margin">Mat. 4. 10.</note> Lord thy God, and him onely ſhalt thou ſerue. If Satans helpe might ſtand a man in ſteede, hee muſt haue no fellowſhip with his vnfruitfull workes of darkenes.</p>
            <p>Our Sauiour Chriſt &amp; his Apoſtles would none of his aſſiſtance to helpe <note place="margin">Eph. 5. 11.</note> to publiſh the Goſpell to the world. It was the bane of <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Ahaziah</hi> Kings of <hi>Iudah,</hi> to ſeeke for helpe of Sathan: It is better to truſt in the <note place="margin">Mat. 1. 25. 1. Cor. 10. 13</note> Lord, then to put any confidence in man, or euil ſpirit, for diuels cannot free vs from the hands of God, <note place="margin">2. Kin. 1. 4.</note> but God can keepe vs from the power of diuels: For if God be with vs who <note place="margin">Pſa. 118. 8. Rom. 8. 31.</note> can be againſt vs? Hee is not farre from euery one of vs, he is as our ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow <note place="margin">Act. 17. 27.</note> at our right hand: He is a ſhield
<pb facs="tcp:27149:11"/> to them that truſt in him: He keepeth <note place="margin">Pſal. 121. 5.</note> his people as the apple of his eye, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <note place="margin">Pro. 30. 5.</note> the ſhadow of his wings, and as the mountaines about Ieruſalem, ſo is <note place="margin">Pſal. 17. 8.</note> the Lord about his people, henceforth <note place="margin">Pſal. 125. 2.</note> and for euer. Say therefore vnto Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, I defie thy power, and renounce thy helpe, as I am none of thine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I am bought with a price, ſo will <note place="margin">1. Cor. 6. 19. 20. Pſal. 181.</note> I none of thee nor of thy helpe: The Lord is my helper, my rocke, my fortreſſe, my deliuerer, m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtrength, my ſhield the horne of my ſaluation, and <note place="margin">Pſal. 17. 1.</note> my refuge, my light, ſaluation, and ſtrength of my life; my defence is in God, who preſerueth the vpright in <note place="margin">Pſal. 78. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> heart. The God whom I ſerue, is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to deliuer me, and though he ſlay <note place="margin">Dan. 3. 17.</note> me I will truſt in him: Hee onely maketh me to dwel in ſafety; the Lord is with me, therefore I will not not feare what man or Sathan can doe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me; For when my fleſh faileth, and <note place="margin">Iob. 13. 15.</note> my heart alſo, then God is the ſtrength <note place="margin">Pſal. 4. 8. Pſal. 73 26.</note> of my heart, and my portion for euer: So the father of mercyes, and the God of all comfort, proſper &amp; ſanctifie that I haue written vnto you.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:27149:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
